Guide to the Richard L. Watson, Jr. Papers, 1941 - 1989 UA.29.02.0041
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard L. Watson, Jr. papers
1941 - 1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Watson, Richard L., 1914-2000
UA.29.02.0041
19 Linear Feet
Richard L. Watson, Jr. served as Professor of History at Duke University (1939-1984), Chair of the Department of History (1960-1967), Chair of the Academic Council (1964-1966, 1975-1977), and associate editor of the South Atlantic Quarterly (1974-1987). Papers include correspondence, notes, committee minutes and reports, course evaluations, research files, and manuscript drafts of chapters, and involve Watson's work with the Army Air Force Historical Office, the History Department, Duke University, professional organizations, research and writings in American history and historiography, and personal materials. English.
14,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Richard L. Watson, Jr. Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1960-1992.
Biographical Note
Richard Lyness Watson, Jr. was born December 25, 1914 in Mount Hermon, Mass. He attended Mount Hermon Preparatory School and graduated 1931. He studied economics and history at Yale University, receiving his B.A. in 1935, and his Ph.D. in 1939. Immediately after attaining his doctorate he moved to Durham and began teaching at Duke University. He was drafted into the Army in 1941 and commissioned in May 1943. He first served at the Coast Artillery School until appointed to the Army Air Force Historical Office. While at this post he served as chief of the Southwest Pacific Branch and was responsible for selecting documents on and writing histories pertaining to the Pacific theatre of operations during the War. His work was ultimately included in the seven volume series, The Army Air Forces in World War II, edited by Wesley Frank Craven and James Lea Cate.
During his forty-five year tenure at Duke, Watson served as one of the university's leading "citizens." He not only served in positions of leadership at the departmental level, but at the university level as well. Duke recognized his citizenship in 1988 when they awarded him the Duke University Medal for Distinguished Meritorious Service. While trained to specialize in early 19th century American history, Watson filled a needed role in the Department of History by shifting his research and teaching focus to early twentieth-century American history. His particular interests lay in the Progressive, Depression, and New Deal Eras. He chaired the department from 1960-1967 and stood in as Acting Chair in 1970-1971 and 1980. He took a lead in the burgeoning development of Black Studies, teaching several summer workshops for college professors on the materials of black history.
Watson led, at numerous points in his career, the faculty's most important representative bodies. He was vice chair of the University Council from 1961-1962; Chairman of the Academic Council from 1964-1966, as well as 1975-1977; and vice chair of the Academic Council from 1973-1974. He was the first person to hold the position of Faculty Secretary of the Academic Council, a position created in 1984. In addition, he was a member of the board of the Duke University Press from 1973-1982, and was associate editor of the South Atlantic Quarterly from 1974-1987. Watson also played a central role in the faculty movement to bar the Nixon presidential library from locating at Duke.
Watson answered the university administration's call to service. This is evidenced in the numerous committees, advisory councils, and task forces to which he was appointed. He played a significant role in helping define and implement university policies during student unrest of the late 1960s. As chair of the Committee on Judicial Procedures he helped put into place judicial procedures and policies to deal with the pickets and protests regulations. He also served on the Faculty Committee on Student Concerns which helped develop policies in response to the takeover of the Allen Building in 1969 and his work on the Student-Faculty-Administration Committee addressed drug policies, military recruitment on campus, and the pickets policy.
Watson served as President of the Southern Historical Association (1976-77) and of the Historical Society of North Carolina (1972-73); he was also chair of the Organization of American Historians' Frederick Jackson Turner Prize Committee from 1964-68. In addition, he sat on the board of editors of both the Mississippi Valley Historical Review (1958-60) and the Journal of Southern History (1968-70). He was a member of the Board of Trustees of St. Augustine's College from 1965-1971.
His activity in the Durham community was recognized by the Duke University Campus Ministry, who in 1992 awarded him its Humanitarian Service Award. Watson aided in the establishment of the St. Philip's Community Kitchen and the Durham Urban Ministry Center. He was also a familiar face in community theater, as a long-time member of Durham Savoyards, a group that presents annual performances of Gilbert and Sullivan.
In the midst of his teaching and academic service, Watson continued to conduct and publish scholarly research. He won the R.D.W. Connor Award for the best article to appear in the North Carolina Historical Review in both 1960 and 1965. He contributed greatly to the teaching of history in the secondary schools by his editorship, along with William Cartwright, of Interpreting and Teaching American History (196?) and its revised edition, Reinterpretation of American History and Culture. Other books he authored or edited include, Bishop Cannon's Own Story, the United States in the Contemporary World, 1945-62, and The Development of National Power: The United States 1900-1919.
Upon retirement in 1984, Watson continued his relationship with Duke. He was active in the university's FOCUS program, as well as hosting Japanese students from Hosei University each year.
Richard L. Watson, Jr. died on September 22, 2000.
Collection Overview
The materials in this collection consist of the papers of Richard L. Watson, Jr. accrued between 1941 and 1989. The majority of the collection pertains to his work at Duke University, both in the department of history and in service to university faculty and administration. There are also papers relating to his writings and research, his work in the Army Air Force Historical Office, professional organizations, and personal life. Types of materials include correspondence, notes, committee minutes and reports, teacher course evaluations, chapter files and draft chapters.
Related Material
Dept. of History records.
University Archives, Duke University.
United States -- History -- Study and teaching; South Atlantic quarterly; Historiography -- United States; Duke University. Department of History; Duke University. Academic Council; Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Faculty; United States. Army Air Forces. Historical Office; Watson, Richard L., 1914-2000; Watson, Richard L., 1914-2000
- Army Air Force Historical Office, 1941-1951
  Scope and Contents note
  The first series, Army Air Force Historical Office, contains material Watson collected while serving as the Chief of the Southwest Pacific Branch of the Army Air Force Historical Office. The work of the office was eventually collected in the seven volume series, The Army Air Forces in World War II, edited by Wesley Frank Craven and James Lea Cate. Watson's contributions to the series pertain chiefly to Vols. I and IV. Types of material in this series include general correspondence about the work of the Historical Office, newspaper clippings chronicling daily events, and notes taken from primary wartime documents on Southwest Pacific Air Operations. Major events include Rabaul, Battle of the Bismarck Sea, Philippines campaign, Pearl Harbor, Wau, and Nassau Bay. Strategic topics include bombing techniques, equipment, men and morale, radio and radar, supplies, and allocations. There are also draft chapters of his work, The Fifth Air Force in the Huon Peninsula Campaign. Also included are several reference works such as maps of the Southwest Pacific, a gazetteer of New Guinea, and several works by J.V. Cragg on the Fifth Air Force.
  - Army Air Force Historical Office (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
  - Drafts
    - Undated, [3 folders] (Box 1)
    - Chapters 1-3, The Fifth Air Force in the Huon Peninsula Campaign (Box 1)
    - Chapters 4-6, The Fifth Air Force in the Huon Peninsula Campaign (Box 1)
  - Notes, The Fifth Air Force in the Huon Peninsula Campaign (Box 1)
  - Fifth Air Force
    - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-Aug. 1943 (Box 1)
    - Sept.-Dec. 1943 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-Feb. 1944 (Box 1)
    - March 1944 (Box 1)
    - April 1944 (Box 1)
    - May 1944 (Box 1)
    - June 1944 (Box 1)
    - July 1944 (Box 1)
    - August 1944 (Box 1)
    - Sept.-Dec. 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes, Fifth Air Force, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    Includes Philippines campaign and Pearl Harbor.
  - Notes on Southwest Pacific Air Operations, n.d., [12 folders] (Box 2)
    Includes notes on Allocation, Australia, Bases (General), Bombing Technique, Bombers (Light), B-25 and B-26, B-24 and B-17, Bibliography, Appendix, SWPA-Oct. 1943, Plans, Service, Rabaul, Operations, SWPA Jan. 44, Appendix, Bibliography, Unit Histories, Problems with men and materials, Organization, Personnel, Photos, Plans, Rabaul, Radio and Radar, Shipping and Supply; Supply dropping, Status, Training, Troop Carrier, Tsili Tsili, Wau, Strategic Situation, Plans and Allocations, Service Command, Preliminary Offensive Moves, Bismarck Sea, Nassau Bay, Part II, Conclusions, Citations, Dobodura, Darwin, Fighters, Intelligence, Miscellaneous, Modifications and Maintenance, Night Fighters.
  - Notes on Southwest Pacific Air Operations, October 1943-February 1944, [3 folders] (Box 2)
    Includes notes on Bases, Allocations, Enemy order of battle, Miscellaneous Morale, Navy, Operations cables, Operations-General, Organization, Personnel, Plans after Jan. 1944, Radar, Service, Status, Supply and Maintenance, Training, Miscellaneous.
  - Notes
    - Battle of the Bismarck Sea, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Southwest Pacific Theater, Sept.-Oct. 1944 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Southwest Pacific Theater, Nov. 1944-Feb. 1945 (Box 2)
  - Outline for a Published History of the AAF, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Paper Critique: Prewar Military Plans and Preparations, 1939-1941 by Maurice Matloff, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Crabb, Brigadier General J.V. Role of Fifth Air Force in Southwest Pacific Campaign, World War II (Box 2, Oversize-folder 3)
  - Crabb, Brigadier General J.V. Fifth Air Force Air War Against Japan, September 1942- August 1945 (Box 2)
  - Gazetteer of South-East New Guinea and New Britain (Box 2)
  - Map. Eastern New Guinea and Bismarck Archipelago (Box 2)
  - Map. Southwest Pacific. (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook. Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
- History Department, 1946-1986
  The materials in the second series, History Department, contain information relating to Watson's forty-five year tenure in the department both as a professor and administrator. Insights into his teaching style can be gleaned from numerous teacher-course evaluations as well as syllabi and book lists. The series contains thirty-five years of correspondence primarily relating to departmental and teaching matters. Also included are departmental meeting minutes, enrollment statistics, and materials relating to graduate students. This series includes numerous planning and curriculum reports, the bulk dating from the 1960s to early 1970s. There is also a run of the departmental publication Research Notes (Nos. 1-14), which describes the scholarly research of faculty members. The development of the departmental honors program is detailed as well as the early history of teaching African-American history at Duke. This series also contains historical information on the activities of the Trinity College Historical Society, a social and professional society for faculty and graduate students of the History Department.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Curriculum of the Department of History, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Curriculum of the Department of History, Report, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the History Graduate Program, Report, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Afro-American History Faculty Appointment, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Afro-American History, 1968-1972 (Box 4)
  - Budgets, 1961-1968, 1980-1982, [8 folders] (Box 4)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    NOTE: Budgets are RESTRICTED; contain salary, evaluation, and motions information.
  - By-Laws, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Courses, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Honors, 1955, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Hyphens and Commas, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Committee to Review Graduate History Curriculum, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Teaching the Social Studies, 1957-1975 (Box 4)
  - Committee on the Seminar Room [William K. Boyd Seminar Room], 1957 (Box 4)
  - Commonwealth Seminar, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1946-1963, [16 folders] (Box 4)
    - 1964-1973, 1980-1981, [11 folders] (Box 5)
      During the fall of 1971, Watson was on a Fulbright in Australia.
  - Course Offerings, 1955-65 (Box 5)
  - Dean's Memoranda, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Dean's Memoranda, 1983-85 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Committee on the Graduate Program, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Leave Requests, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Meeting Minutes
    - 1953, 1958-61, 1965-67 (Box 5)
    - 1962-64 (Box 5)
    - 1968-75 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Search Committee, 1974-75 (Box 5)
    NOTE: Search Committee files are RESTRICTED.
  - Education, Department of, 1961-65 (Box 5)
  - Enrollment Statistics
    - 1976 (Box 5)
    - 1979 (Box 5)
    - 1982 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1967-75 (Box 5)
  - Faculty Rosters, 1980-83 (Box 5)
  - General Education Board Southern Scholarships, 1950-53 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Alumni Correspondence, 1965-67 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Staff, 1961-64 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Student Committee on Curriculum Reform-Report, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Students
    NOTE: Student records are RESTRICTED.
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 5)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1972 (Box 5)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 5)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Studies, Director of, 1957-60 (Box 5)
  - Graduate History 1 and 2 (50 and 51), Syllabi, n.d. (Box 6)
  - History 1X, 1959-63 (Box 6)
  - History 91, Teacher Course Evaluations, n.d. (Box 6)
  - History 91-92, 1947-52 (Box 6)
  - History 113, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1972 (Box 6)
  - History 113, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1974 (Box 6)
  - History 114, Teacher Course Evaluations, n.d. [ca. 1970s] (Box 6)
  - History 114, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1975 (Box 6)
  - History 114, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1980 (Box 6)
  - History 196D, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1971 (Box 6)
  - History 212, Teacher Course Evaluations, 1971 (Box 6)
  - History Alumni, Fund Raising, 1977-80 (Box 6)
  - History Majors. Statistics, 1955-66 (Box 6)
  - History of India Vacancy, 1972-73 (Box 6)
  - History of Science, 1962-64 (Box 6)
  - History Sub-Committee on Interdisciplinary Programs, 1967-68 (Box 6)
  - Honors Program, 1963-64 (Box 6)
  - Honors Program, Proposals and Ideas, 1958-60 (Box 6)
  - Independent Study, 1970-75 (Box 6)
  - Independent Study, 1980-84 (Box 6)
  - Library Reserve Book Lists, ca. 1981 (Box 6)
  - Makerere University College Exchange Program, 1967-70 (Box 6)
  - Medical Historian Training Program, 1967 (Box 6)
  - National Defense Fellowship, 1958-61 (Box 6)
  - NEH Summer Workshop on the Materials for Teaching Negro History, 1968-70
    - Applicants, 1968, [2 folders] (Box 6)
    - Budget, 1968-70 (Box 6)
    - Publishers, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Paranavitana, Senarat Lecture, 1962, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Planning, 1958-66 (Box 6)
  - Planning Committee of the Dept. of History, 1973-74 (Box 6)
  - Pre-Major Advising, 1986-88 (Box 6)
  - Report: Department of History, "An Ongoing Program", [1965] (Box 6)
  - Report of the Planning Committee of the Dept. of History, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Report of Special Long-Range Planning Committee for the History Dept., 1964 (Box 6)
  - Research Notes (#1-14), 1982-84 (Box 6)
  - Self-Study Committee on the Curriculum-Report, [ca. 1976] (Box 6)
  - Summer Session, 1960-63 (Box 6)
  - Summer Session, 1963-64 (Box 6)
  - Teaching Course Load, 1976-79 (Box 6)
  - Trinity College Historical Society
    - 1958-1972 (Box 6)
    - 1973-1977 (Box 6)
    - 1978-1986 (Box 6)
    - Newsletters, 1978-79, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Undergraduate Studies, Director of, 1959-60 (Box 6)
- University, 1947-1988
  The third series, University, documents Watson's involvement and service on numerous faculty and university committees, councils, and task forces. Watson served as vice chair of the University Council from 1961-62; Chairman of the Academic Council from 1964-66, as well as 1975-77; and vice chair of the Academic Council from 1973-74. Materials relating to the University Council document discussion about tuition benefits for faculty children, by-laws, faculty qualification and improvements, and the role of University Council. His long service on the Undergraduate Faculty Council (UFC) and Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS) is reflected in this series. He chaired the UFC Faculty Committee on Admissions and the minutes and report are contained in these files. He also was appointed to the review committee on the structure of UFCAS. In addition, in the early 1970s Watson was on the executive committee of the Undergraduate Faculty Committee of Arts and Sciences. These files include a proposal on Afro-American studies.
  Watson was appointed to numerous university committees formed in response to the period of student protest and unrest of the late 1960s. This series contains minutes, reports, correspondence, and background material from said committees. The Committee on Judicial Procedures, also called the "Watson Committee", was created to define and implement judicial procedures and address the pickets and protests regulations. The files contain committee reports, meeting minutes, background materials and correspondence. They also include information on the existing judicial structures and procedures of the Men's Student Government Association, the Women's Student Government Association, and the Nursing and Medical Schools. There is also information on honor codes as embedded in the judicial structures. The materials from the Faculty Committee on Student Concerns relate to the Allen Building takeover, Afro-American studies program, and the Afro-American society. The Student-Faculty-Administration Committee files contain information relating to university drug policy, military recruitment on campus, and pickets and protest policies.
  In 1981, Duke President Terry Sanford proposed Duke as a possible site for the Richard M. Nixon presidential library. Watson played a central role in faculty debate over the appropriateness of placing the library at Duke. This series contains news clippings, correspondence, academic council material, and his own diary and notes on the controversy.
  Materials in this series relating to the Committee on Social Implications of Duke's Investment Policy all appear to be originals from committee co-chair William A. Reppy and chairman James D. Cox's files. The committee consisted of twelve members appointed by the President and included four administrators, four faculty members, and four students. The committee was allowed to make specific recommendations or general guidelines to the Board of Trustees. It primarily dealt with issues relating to investments with companies doing business with South Africa. This collection of materials includes news articles, church shareholder resolutions, correspondence, and minutes.
  Other committees and subjects addressed in this series include the Task Force on Yearly Operations, the Institute of Policy Studies and Public Affairs, the library council and the George Washington Flowers Collection, the Forest History Society, Phi Beta Kappa, the South Atlantic Quarterly, and the YMCA.
  - Academic Council. Committee on Faculty and Staff Housing, 1963-65 (Box 7)
  - Academic Council. Committee on Trustee Nominations [info on student trustees], 1974, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Academic Freedom, 1965-76 (Box 7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on African and Afro-American Studies, 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Alumni Lecture Series, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Alumni Lecture Series, 1965-68 (Box 7)
  - American Association of University Professors-Duke University Chapter, 1978-87 (Box 7)
  - Angier B. Duke Scholarship (on finals committee), 1972-73 (Box 7)
  - Art Museum Siting Committee, 1988-89 (Box 7)
  - Art Museum Siting Committee, 1989-91 (Box 7)
  - Baldwin Federation, 1978-79 (Box 7)
  - Baldwin Federation, 1979-80 (Box 7)
  - Bassett Affair, 75th Anniversary, 1978-79 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Celebration of Teacher Education in Duke University, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Center for Commonwealth Studies, 1979-88 (Box 7)
  - Center for Southern Studies, 1965-66 (Box 7)
  - Colloquium 101, [1962] (Box 7)
  - Commencement Marshals, 1950-52 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Judicial Procedures
    - 1968 (Box 7)
    - 1969, [2 folders] (Box 7)
    - Background Material, 1968-69 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 7)
    - Existing Duke Judicial Structures and Procedures, 1965-69 (Box 7)
    - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1968-69 (Box 7)
    - Policies at Other Institutions, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Reports, 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Planning and Development. Sub-Committee on the University Arts Center, 1958-60 (Box 7)
  - Committee on School Management, 1981-82 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Social Implications of Duke's Investment Policy (Box 8)
    - Articles on Alternate Sources of Energy, 1978-79 (Box 8)
    - Articles on Chile and Argentina, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Articles on Military Arms Sales, 1978-79 (Box 8)
    - Articles on Nuclear Energy, 1978-79 (Box 8)
    - Articles on South Africa and Uganda, 1977-79 (Box 8)
    - Church Shareholder Resolutions, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1977-80 (Box 8)
    - Corporate Examiner, 1978-79 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1981-82 (Box 8)
    - Minutes, 1978-80 (Box 8)
    - Minutes, 1981-82 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Articles, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Xerox Corporation, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Student Counseling on Military Service, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Committee to Recommend a Successor to Dean Marcus Hobbs, 1962-63 (Box 8)
  - Dean of Arts and Sciences, Search Committee, 1984-85 (Box 8)
  - Dean of Trinity College, Replacement Selection Committee, 1963-64 (Box 8)
  - Duke Elderhostel, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Duke United Fund Campaign, 1963-66 (Box 8)
    Includes information on desegregation of Durham YMCA.
  - Duke United Way Campaign, 1977-84 (Box 8)